<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title></title>
		<description>Indie Game development</description>
		<link>/</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>New Home!</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Hey folks! I’m Just posting here to annouce our new blog.
After a long time we finaly moved our site from wordpress.com to sheetcoldgames.me.
Our new home is hosted on github(yes, open source) and is jekyll powered. This layout is not final, we still have some changes to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Btw, this is my first post here. I will try to post more often (and that’s a lie).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/general/news/2015/07/27/new-home.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/general/news/2015/07/27/new-home.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>LD32 and back to business</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Oh wow, is this right again? The last update was... (1, 2, 3, 4, 5...) six months ago?? Yes, it was. First we&#39;ll start by apologizing the lack of posts and all, but we all have our little personal problems, right? Right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, in this blog post we&#39;ll be talking about what we&#39;re up to and what we&#39;ve done. So here it comes. As usual, I&#39;ll be talking through my (Rafael) perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What changed after a year of Ludum Dare?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, a lot of things have changed since the last time I entered a Ludum Dare, which was last year. I thought to myself that game jams could be cool and I didn&#39;t notice back in that time but I was definitely not ready for a game jam. The only time I&#39;d done anything related to a jam was at the &lt;a title=&quot;We were at the Global Game Jam 2014!!!&quot; href=&quot;/global game jam/2014/01/30/we-were-at-the-global-game-jam-2014.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GGJ 2014&lt;/a&gt; and I thought I could make something cause, hell, it&#39;s been 3 months since the GGJ, I can TOTALLY make a game in 3 days. My mindset was still not focused on gameplay, but on delivering stories and emotions through images and music. My lack of experience with any programming tool forced me into trying to find any shortcut in order to deliver what I wanted to. But I noticed what happened back in the day only now. There are differences between the technical approach to game development and the way people perceive games. One is actually a clearer subject than another, but the point here is that I had to actually understand what I was doing or it would be hard to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what really changed in one year? As a person, I can&#39;t say that much has really changed, but my view about games are somewhat different, I feel like this might be the actual start of everything that we want to create. Anyway, let&#39;s talk about this LD32.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The theme was announced, we didn&#39;t actually feel good about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me and Gabriel had been talking about taking a break from our current project to actually give 72h of our time to LD, but we didn&#39;t consider that the theme could be something that we didn&#39;t want to make. I followed all the rounds of elimination of the themes, picking the ones I liked and downvoting the ones I didn&#39;t like only to notice that a theme which had won one of the rounds had the most votes out of all rounds. This made me feel a bit worried, but I always hold my hopes up in terms of wanting things, so I waited. When the theme was announced, that&#39;s what we got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;&lt;strong&gt;An Unconventional Weapon&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has got to be the worst theme of all LDs I followed ever since two and a half years ago. I saw a lot of people on twitter giving up when they realized this was the theme and it all was pretty divided, some people loved it a lot and some people hated it a lot. We didn&#39;t like the theme, but we had already announced that we were going to participate, so what were we up to do? Bail? Face it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we decided it was good for us to just participate. We came up with a lot of regular, shitty and 18+ ideas, some of them included a character holding a mirror (&lt;a title=&quot;Mirroir du Mort&quot; href=&quot;http://ludumdare.com/compo/2015/04/20/miroir-du-mort-third-and-almost-final-build/comment-page-1/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;wow, did somebody ACTUALLY made a game about this?&lt;/a&gt;) eventually it had passed 5 hours and I didn&#39;t make anything for the game and Gabriel was doodling with a limited palette. We didn&#39;t notice back then, but that procrastination would make for some amazing practice for this LD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The ideas felt a bit blurry, but we move on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to think about our current situation. These months of march and april were really special for us. Gabriel started participating in &lt;a title=&quot;Pixel Dailies Twitter&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Pixel_Dailies&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;#pixel_dailies&lt;/a&gt; and I started as well to help him and SheetColdGames out. This gave us not only some followers, but some insight about the work of other indie devs along the way. So we decided to work on something less serious, we were already doing something serious to be released and we thought that maybe we could have some fun and practice with this LD. If people hate it, if it is buggy or anything, it doesn&#39;t matter. At least we&#39;ll have some fun. So we decided to work on a theme based on a mysterious man with a crow mask that throws chickens on skeletons that decided to bother his calm life near the graveyard. We didn&#39;t think of details at that time, and more than 15 hours of LD had already passed. I had only a square on the screen and decided to implement some basic mechanics, but everything was still quite not clear. Anyway, Gabriel thinks of the main character in a monochromatic way, which is a good think, cause it helps him becoming a better artist. I was pretty calm at the time, I never actually wanted to do this theme and all, but after a good sleep (and by good, I mean almost 10 hours), I was ready to code until I was dead tired. So after some time thinking of what I should do next after I handled the collisions and the chicken throwing, I decided to have the brilliant idea of having an in game editor so people could tweak the only level of the game and have some fun with debugging and trolling their friends. Anyway, it was a nice concept, but extremely risky! I have already done a collision editor before, but it was buggy, could I make not only the walls editor, but the scenario editor as well? You will see that some things never change and my way of thinking I&#39;m the superman is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The editor sounded like a good idea. Oh, it was so cool! Oh, what a terrible idea!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So coding the editor was surprisingly fun! Specially when you don&#39;t have to care about the looks of the code. Even though it was a game jam, it was still a surprisingly good looking editor in the ins and outs. I mean, it didn&#39;t feature any explanation on how to use it IN the editor, but give me a break. The editor I coded first was the collision walls editor. This editor was inspired by the UbiArt Framework videos I&#39;ve seen. So collisions are handled in lines which you control the points. The secret of my collision detection is an ArrayList (for non Java people, this is a dynamic array) of LinkedLists. Why did I do this way? I think it&#39;s better to leave this explanation on some later article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I thought about the editor of the characters, but since I was dead tired from the other editor, I decided to leave this later cause my body was not responding well for almost 30 hours awoken with only 2 hours of rest. So I decided to take some nap and GODDAMN six hours of sleep, how much time til LD ends? 10 hours?! Ok ok, I just needed the character editor, the map editor... The renderer for the character. The enemies abilities, the boss... The level design.... Well, well... well. I thought I could do this!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten hours and lots of stuff to do, I thought I was gonna probably hate this...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Near the end, an internal surprise. A good surprise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I don&#39;t recall eating too much, oh yeah, cause I didn&#39;t. I ate a piece of bread after I woke up and went straight into the computer to program. Only a miracle would bring a game with all of those things that were missing, but I needed to get them done somehow. While I was with Gabriel (art) on Skype, we didn&#39;t had too much time to think of a game, we had already that, but something was different. Something interesting was happening. We were actually enjoying that theme, somehow. We never actually think of dumb things to implement, but that was fun. And even though I was getting more and more stressed out (probably cause my back was killing me after hours sitting in the same position), I was happy with the result. We had definitely turned out something that we hate it into something that we loved. And somehow the game was coming together, the physics were a mess, the character didn&#39;t feature all the animations, AI was batshit dumb, we missed the background and there were no SFX (I even forgot the music on one of the build fixes!), but it was fun and we were laughing until the 2 final hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last hour before the release, Gabriel lost internet connection, I still didn&#39;t have a map design editor and that made finishing the game with something playable a hard test. By then we&#39;re here having almost nothing if the main game was not finished. By some blessing, Gabriel&#39;s internet comes back with a small draft of a map in Tiled. That was enough to say that we actually created something. Now we could release the project as something small. I put a small track together, and we are up and running&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;After the end: stress and joy mashes together. But something doesn&#39;t feel right... At least for me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the deadline arrived, it didn&#39;t feel like the end. I needed to definitely work more in the game, the final editor was not done, there were no SFX, the AI needed improvement, we needed a boss and etc... But something felt wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make the editor, making editors was fun and all, but I didn&#39;t want to rush because of the game. Even though the game was funny, it didn&#39;t mean that I was excited to move along. And here&#39;s where Rafael as a person probably didn&#39;t change. I remember the last LD where I put all my efforts to make Beneath Lights more interesting, really, I&#39;m talking 3 days of effort. There was an internal motivation in terms of making people understand what I was trying to implement and that made me worry if it was good enough or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point, I believe it was good, at the other point... I really don&#39;t know. What I know is that I wasn&#39;t motivated to finish this last LD32 and I probably won&#39;t be. That&#39;s the reason making games is sort of difficult for me. I have to balance this underlying thin line of gameplay and story. You might say I&#39;m completely wrong. Other SCG fellows might also disagree. But that is just me. I like the technical difficulties of games, even though it is cool to remove one of the difficulties, it is also less motivating for me. So I&#39;d probably do something harder to create in terms of concepts and ideas than just something technical. Call me crazy. Anyway, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gamejolt.com/games/platformer/the-silent-rage-of-the-chicken-throwing-crow-masked-man/61783/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the game is available to download here through GameJolt&lt;/a&gt;. Depending on how things go in the future, I might even just finish this game, who knows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More updates about what we&#39;re up to coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;--&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;Rafael Giordanno&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 20:47:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/game%20jam/global%20game%20jam/ludum%20dare/2015/05/05/ld32-and-back-to-business.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/game%20jam/global%20game%20jam/ludum%20dare/2015/05/05/ld32-and-back-to-business.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Silent Rage of the Chicken Throwing Crow Masked Man</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; size-full wp-image-135 alignnone&quot; src=&quot;/assets/media/banner.png&quot; alt=&quot;TSROTCTCMM Banner&quot; width=&quot;360&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rafael&#39;s second and Gabriel&#39;s debut in Ludum Dare. The theme was &quot;An Unconventional Weapon&quot;. They didn&#39;t like so much, but they had agreed in making something and thus this happened. Rafael&#39;s not sure if he&#39;ll work on it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LD32 happened on april 17th to april 20th&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/games/game%20jam/2015/04/20/the-silent-rage-of-the-chicken-throwing-crow-masked-man.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/games/game%20jam/2015/04/20/the-silent-rage-of-the-chicken-throwing-crow-masked-man.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Adrift in Space</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-136&quot; src=&quot;/assets/media/thumbnail-astronaut_peum.png?w=687&quot; alt=&quot;AIS_Astronaut&quot; width=&quot;687&quot; height=&quot;458&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concept implemented for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itch.io/jam/gdp-space-jam&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GDP Space Jam&lt;/a&gt; that Rafael had for LD30 theme Connected Worlds which he couldn&#39;t implement for thinking it was too complex. He did all the concept for the full game in five hours. The rest of the time was doing star effects, collectible effects, the OST and polishing the controls to make a little fairer. The game is quite complicated and practically unbeatable for most people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://itch.io/jam/gdp-space-jam&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GDP Space Jam&lt;/a&gt; happened on February 27th to March 1st&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/games/game%20jam/2015/03/01/adrift-in-space.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/games/game%20jam/2015/03/01/adrift-in-space.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>In Memory of my Friend, G976</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/in-memory-of-art-resized.png?w=687&quot; alt=&quot;In memory of Art (resized)&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our second game for the Global Game Jam 2015, a year later and some improvements can be seen from our debut game. It&#39;s still under final touches, a blog post and download link will come soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Global Game Jam 2015 happened on January 23rd.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0200</pubDate>
				<link>/games/global%20game%20jam/2015/01/23/in-memory-of-my-friend-g976.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/games/global%20game%20jam/2015/01/23/in-memory-of-my-friend-g976.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>GBJam3 review and future plans</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, folks. Rafael here again. Wow, is the title correct? Yes it is! This time we&#39;re updating (late) details of the GBJam and the current plans we have for the future of SheetColdGames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we stated in the previous post, we were on the GBJam and did a great job for a debut game, starring at #48 on the rank of more than 200 games, even with a game with no sound, I was pretty glad that people enjoyed the overall unfinished experience. OK, so let me share the experience of the GBJam before it slips away from my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A totally new experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there&#39;s one word that can describe the GBJam for me is: NIGHTMARE! Calm down, it&#39;s not the way you think it is. Everything was great, the tweets and previews that people posted were super cool, the whole interaction on twitter was amazing. Now if there was really a problem, that had got to be me (Rafael). For this GBJam game, I decided to go with a tactical strategy game in the shape of games I played when I was little, like Shining Force, Final Fantasy Tactics Advance and Phantasy Star. The only problem with that was: I never had any experience on creating games like that. I always wanted to make tactical strategy games, but my main problem was that I never knew how to start. The movement? The battle? The A.I.? The cutscenes? The attack animations? The stats? How do I store all these stuff? Somehow down the line, things started to come together (in a very ugly way internally) and I was able to have an idea of a game after 4 or 5 days. The main problem that I faced while making the game was the A.I., I didn&#39;t know how to implement the A.I. logic for the whole game so that it felt good. Another problem that emerged was the combat system, but I&#39;ll get to that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the GBJam started, I knew that I wanted to make a tactical strategy game, so I did a little mockup on how I thought the game would look like, after some hours drawing pixel by pixel, I came up with this (notice that this is pre-GBJam):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-102&quot; src=&quot;/assets/media/game-mockup.png&quot; alt=&quot;clockwork mockup&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;216&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ok, nothing so fancy, but again, I am no artist. I thought that was enough for me to know how the game would look like in the end. I had a simple HUD, everyone understood what I wanted, so I was on the right track. When the GBJam began, I started programming everything with filled rectangles and did the background logic. That&#39;s when I noticed I wasn&#39;t planning ahead all the stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When (almost) everything began to go wrong,&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I didn&#39;t focus on creating a core engine was because I thought I would make everything on my own. I really thought I would be able to make a full enjoyable lengthy game with art and music in 10 days without having any idea on how to start doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My gut only took me so far. At the end of day one, I was having only the basic movement for the main character... And it was so flawed that desperated me a little bit. &quot;How can the movement in a top down game be flawed?&quot; I might hear you ask. Well, the player was only allowed to move inside the 16/16 pixel grid I had set up. The reason for me to want that was to prevent any strange movements in the game and keep  it fluid, else, the player would think (s)he could be able to move outside the grid and that was not the intention. Several games implemented move in that way, one example is Shining Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I started out pretty slow, I still believed that things would go well. I had already started doing other stuff pretty slow at the beginning, ending up with full fledged systems in less than 6 days, so I thought that would be the same with this game. Only one problem I didn&#39;t notice was I NEVER MADE THIS TYPE OF GAME. It took me that time in the past because I&#39;d only worked with platforming games. I really thought that physics in a platform game was easier than the constraints of the top down strategy game. Well, you might say: &quot;Dude, it IS easier&quot;, again, I never worked on this type game. So I should&#39;ve planned in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, at the dawn of the second day, I found Victor Moura, who was wanting to create a game for the GBJam but wasn&#39;t feeling really inspired. Later on, I, not only, found out he had created beautiful pixel art. But that he also had made the art for Terraria. After showing him the mockup presented early on in this post, he remade everything with different colors in about 3 hours and this was the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-104&quot; src=&quot;/assets/media/0vznk3k.gif&quot; alt=&quot;clockwork gui remade&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; height=&quot;144&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I was blown away and sold at the first second. It was an honour to have him on board and his dedication made me push my skills further to have that type of game done already. Working with Victor was the first time I have ever worked with someone commited to do the work and to really share ideas. At first sight, I felt like some sort of boss, since I was the one with the vision for the final game. I never like this sort of boss type of hierarchy, I&#39;m not really paying him, so I wanted to allow him to have ideas as well. In somewhat like 2 days, we started to develop a better conversation with ourselves sharing tons of ideas and talking about a million different stuff. It was a pleasant experience and I only wished I had more experience to, at least, make some stuff better in the game. But it was a good learning experience, he was super patient with my dedication to the project and I&#39;m glad I spent those days working with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The critical moment, only four days left&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With four days left, I still didn&#39;t have any sprites on the screen, just rectangles with the temporary tiles for collision and movement. Even like that, I was pretty happy with the result of having a flawed path finding algorithm and using a recursive method to find all the possible walking tiles. Now there were other problems, I needed to make the player attack the enemy and vice versa, had to come up with the cutscenes and the menu to tell the story and also had to work my way with the camera movement and the turn based thing as well as the &quot;juice&quot; that would make the game feel cool. Desperation starts to take in and I decided to start working on all the visual stuff already. In one day, much of what you see in the final game is already done and that made me believe in myself again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the few days went by, I ended up noticing that I wouldn&#39;t have the time to insert the music, not only that, but I wasn&#39;t being able to insert music into the game. That made me a little nervous. Of course I wanted to have my music in the game, Victor also wanted, but an internal bug on the way I was implementing didn&#39;t allow that. Not only this, but I noticed that the way I implemented the engine was so flawed that every single instance of the game had to receive the Music Player, cause each instance knows when to play the music. I learned a value lesson after this, which was centralize the instances and the logic of the game. And here is my advice for you, the less parameters each instance of your engine needs, the better. So after, this, we had no sound in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Two days left. Where&#39;s the menu? The sequence of the game?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here I was trying to fix the logic of the A.I. and didn&#39;t notice I had no game so far. No sequence of scenes, of battles, or even a menu. So I decided to work on a game that could have some sort of beginning and end, even though it wouldn&#39;t be enjoyable. And that&#39;s what I did. In one day, I implemented the entire cutscenes for the game and made a sequence. I wouldn&#39;t see the whole cutscenes done until the last minute of the jam. As in terms of A.I. for the game, I could have thought of some better algorithm. But I decided to simply scrap everything and go with the random approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The release of the game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I released the game, it was just a few minutes before the deadline, I was hoping for the worst, but people seemed to enjoy and it was a very nice experience for me. I could think of everything as being a real experience of what a life of a game dev was like and I sort of took that for my life and decided to study a lot more to improve my programming technique. And this is what I&#39;m doing right now. That&#39;s why it took so long to make an update. (not only that, but other internal problems here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And what about the future?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future is uncertain, but we&#39;ll be definitely developing Clockwork Gear Hunters as soon as I establish my life (a job, etc.), From now on, you&#39;ll be reading about the development of Clockwork Gear Hunters and the unnamed engine that we&#39;ll develop so far for 2D games. We&#39;ll be writing it in Java using libGDX, but João Vitor and I have been talking and there&#39;s a possibility of the game being released on C/C++, we still don&#39;t know which framework we might use (IF we use any, else we might just go with OpenGL to help on the rendering). The reason for this change of heart is the fact that all the materials that we found so far are in C/C++ format, port that to Java will be easy later on. So hang on, little buddies, we still alive and we&#39;ll continue to make games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, one last thing. We might be migrating to Jekyll, and we&#39;ll be probably hosting our page on Github Pages, so the blog section will be transferred to there. This one will still be alive and we might (even) update this blog along with the official blog. More about this on the next post. See ya.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 20:45:08 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/game%20jam/news/2014/10/12/gbjam3-review-and-future-plans.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/game%20jam/news/2014/10/12/gbjam3-review-and-future-plans.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Clockwork Gear Hunters (ALPHA)</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/media/clockwork_splash_screen.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clockwork Gear Hunters (GB)&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;288&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our debut game for the GBJam3, Clockwork Gear Hunters is our first Strategy RPG with artwork made by &lt;a title=&quot;Follow this guy, he&#39;s awesome!!!one!&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CrownoO&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Victor Moura&lt;/a&gt;. Long blog entry is being written now. This game is currently in alpha, let us know what you think of it &lt;a href=&quot;http://gamejolt.com/games/strategy-sim/clockwork-gear-hunters/32011/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gamejolt.com/tag/gbjam3&quot;&gt;GBJam3&lt;/a&gt; happened on August 1st to August 10th.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/games/game%20jam/2014/08/10/clockwork-gear-hunters.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/games/game%20jam/2014/08/10/clockwork-gear-hunters.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Long time no see... New jam games on the way</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Rafael here. It&#39;s been quite some time since our last update. But this blog post is intended to show what we did and what we have in mind for the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now there&#39;ll be some jams in a few days (GBJam, Ludum Dare 30), and we can sum up everything so far to &lt;em&gt;FAIL&lt;/em&gt; (or maybe trial and error).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since our last game on the &lt;em&gt;Ludum Dare&lt;/em&gt;, we really wanted to break free from &lt;em&gt;Box2D&lt;/em&gt;, since it is just too much for fake physics platformers. With that, came an idea that we could create something new and better, but it&#39;s just not that simple. So I tried to implement the programming part of a full fledged physics for a platformer game . I developed the map editor and created something quite good that relies on the size of the character sprite (at will) to develop the collision box, which is quite good for movement and fighting games. But to get that right took some time. I re-programmed everything three times and I am about to do it again for the fourth time because of the latest inclusion of an entity system on libGDX 1.2 (I don&#39;t know if it&#39;s good to use it, but I have to try it anyway).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, basically what we were trying to do was to develop a game similar to the ones that we did on LD and GGJ, but we couldn&#39;t. Not only because programming and creating art is hard, but because the themes behind Beneath Lights and Silver Lining are hard to implement in a way that the game makes sense and it&#39;s fun to play. It&#39;s not like we can&#39;t make a simple platformer with a corky sense of humor. It&#39;s just that is going to be a project where we might dedicate months of our lives to create it, so we can&#39;t just make something that we don&#39;t feel proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&#39;s talk about the future, and the future is our debut at GBJam and the new Ludum Dare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jams.gamejolt.io/gbjam3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GBJam &lt;/a&gt;is an event held by &lt;a href=&quot;http://gamejolt.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GameJolt&lt;/a&gt; which consists of developing a game using the game boy audio and video limitations. I believe this compo is really important for us, because the limitations are so big that we don&#39;t even need to care about other graphical stuff, like lights and such. I&#39;m intending to work on the project solo, making the art assets and the music as well. João Vitor might work on the project as soon as he got time (he&#39;s really busy with college and internship), but he&#39;ll try come up with other game. So, at best, we might see two new SCG games in 13 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game boy is quite an impressive device to tackle on, it has only four colors (three for drawing and one for the background). Its sound chip has the same architecture of the NES, except that it doesn&#39;t have a triangle wave form. I&#39;m intending to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://famitracker.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Famitracker&lt;/a&gt; to compose, and to achieve that sound, we have to create a new FDS channel and make it sound similar to the original thing. Good thing we have lots of infos on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the game, I am intending to make a strategy game. So I&#39;m assembling a small engine to achieve that. I&#39;m also drawing the skeleton character for the other characters, since the perspective is different from a platformer. I&#39;m going with a Shadowrun perspective on the game, but since the GB screen is so tiny (160x144) we&#39;ll have a really small character (16x16). I&#39;m still working on the code to make the pallete swap and as always I&#39;m intending to make a full game (even though it might be small like the previous games). It&#39;ll be a great learning experience for me and I hope everybody likes the final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we have Ludum Dare 30. But what can we say about this one? This time, João Vitor will participate on the 72h jam compo and I&#39;m going to tackle on the 48h solo compo. I know it&#39;s a huge leap, but I&#39;m confident of the power of the engine that I&#39;m assembling so far, so does João Vitor. Even though all the code should be rewritten for the 48h compo, I&#39;m confident that I&#39;ll be able to remake everything, it&#39;s good practice. Expect a new platform game coming from us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, be happy! SheetColdGames might bring four new games this month (two or three in the worst case). We hope you guys have lots of fun while playing them and I&#39;ll see you on the GBJam update!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 14:22:47 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/game%20jam/news/2014/07/29/long-time-no-see-new-jam-games-on-the-way.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/game%20jam/news/2014/07/29/long-time-no-see-new-jam-games-on-the-way.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Our first Ludum Dare game - Beneath Lights</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I (Rafael) have participated in the Ludum Dare for the first time. I&#39;ve been wanting to make a game there since LD23, but never thought I had &quot;what it takes&quot; to make a decent game in 48h/72h. But now the game is here, I present you: &lt;a title=&quot;Click here to play&quot; href=&quot;http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-29/?action=preview&amp;amp;uid=34466&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beneath Lights&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-29/?action=preview&amp;amp;uid=34466&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-large wp-image-54&quot; src=&quot;/assets/media/beneath1.png?w=460&quot; alt=&quot;Beneath Lights&quot; width=&quot;460&quot; height=&quot;345&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Post mortem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you don&#39;t want to read all of this stuff, there&#39;s a &lt;a href=&quot;#tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR;&lt;/a&gt; at the end where I bring my experiences earned into account&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;72 hours to think/create, less than 48 to work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:00 PM - The theme was released, I had no time to work immediately, another compo was happening at the same time: Google Code Jam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After deciding to forget about the GCJ, I decided to move into LD and the first hours were tough. At first, Beneath the Surface sounded like a nice theme. But I couldn&#39;t come up with any idea that satisfied myself and the theme limitations. Many objective and subjective thoughts happened at the same time: &quot;A drowning... Excavation... Multiple Layers... Historical background layers&quot; All these ideas could not satisfy my need to create a game that could make me feel proud in the end. So, at 6am, a hard idea appeared and I decided to work in a game that was ready for Mobile and Desktop. By that time, I had already started a simple scene and a small physical world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got home, at 8am (I was at João Vitor&#39;s house because of GCJ), I took some rest thinking that I had a game in mind. When I woke up I kept working on the idea of a shoot and run + Runner game for mobile. The story would make more sense in terms of theming. But when it was 23pm at my time, I had almost nothing from the game I had in mind, so I decide to scrap that idea and think of something new. After two hours of brainstorming, a new idea emerged, and that was the concept for Beneath Lights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Removing non-used code and working on the new idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting the new game from 1:00 AM left me with less than 48h to finish it. The new game idea revolved around a man in struggle with his memory constantly thinking of his lost loved one and punishing himself for that (the dark platform maze is a punishing area btw). Most of the ideas (orb, dark maze and lights) were not thought until the last day of the jam. Before that, it was just me drawing the house and creating platforming mechanics. When the whole idea for the game was done, I decided to let the underground become complete darkness and that allowed me to create a game that could fit my vision and let me work around the time limitations and lack of experience on this type of event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this process, I deleted almost all of my code used for the other type of game and things became quite simpler for quite some time. After all, I thought I&#39;d made the right decision with the game changing, but thinking about it on the first day would surely have helped me a lot. By the end of the second day, I had no art and was using placeholders. That&#39;s when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/author/brittbrady/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Britt Brady&lt;/a&gt; saved the day with his music and art. I decided to call for help on LD blog page and he showed up interested. He did the arts super fast and made two awesome tracks for the game (which unfortunately could only fit one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ok, so what was learned through all this process?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my second game jam and obviously several things were learned, here are some tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid hard code things that are not supposed to be hard coded&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And by that, I mean creating maps. I had a super hard time creating the map (a problem that I almost didn&#39;t have with Silver Lining), All the Box2D coordinates were hard coded and that&#39;s plain stupid, so simply try to create an easy way to develop a map editor to just focus on important things, don&#39;t feel ashamed by that. You might even want to play hard mode and just create your map editor during the jam, but if you&#39;re not experienced (as I am not), just use a map editor. Believe me, creating a game with a map editor is hard enough, don&#39;t fool yourself thinking otherwise. There might be other things, but create maps is just the first things that comes into my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Any) Experience counts more than you can imagine:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the GGJ and LD, I had plenty of time to work on learning more about the LibGDX framework. Constantly creating bodies on Box2D and levels with short game mechanics allowed me to make stuff much faster than the previous game and understand problems as soon as they appeared. Real experience creating games is much more important than theoretical experience. Not only that, but we code a lot faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on crucial details early on:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your game is a platformer, focus on get the platforming right before adding new elements (don&#39;t focus too much though, a good enough at the beginning might be improved on the last hours, just don&#39;t leave it buggy). If it&#39;s a ship game, focus on the fact that the gravity revolving your ship should feel right before moving on. If it&#39;s a RPG with text, focus on a smart way to make the text move faster (for debug or even in game) and on the battle mechanics. Focus on the main facts that make your game playable underneath all the art and music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debug tools are very important&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debug tools save a LOT of time, so always create a debug condition for your game and you might be able to test stuff quicker (since you won&#39;t be able to test much stuff for your game anyway). I can&#39;t even count the amount of time I wasted closing and opening the game window just to change one line of code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respect your limitations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that my game is not the greatest game of all LD. It is a short game, its platforming mechanics are far from awesome, but they&#39;re decent. Great part of it is because I like to respect my limitations at this moment. I&#39;d rather create something shorter but nice, than something longer and painful to play (even though some might think Beneath Lights is a bit frustrating). From this game to the previous is pretty much the same mechanics, but they feel different, they play different. The only added element was the light orb, the level design itself is not bigger than Silver Lining, but it&#39;s more ambitious in terms of camera, cutscenes, lights. You should feel challenged, you should feel an evolution from the previous game. And that evolution is only yours. Make sure that your game is a game you want to remember. Not anyone else, only yourself. I truly believe that if you accomplish that, others will follow your opinion and understand you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let&#39;s not forget the environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe it&#39;s important that your overall environment (home, office, whatever...) gives you the freedom to work on your game&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;nav id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ok, TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first experience with Ludum Dare was awesome and tough at the same. I learned a lot and truly felt an evolution from the previous game. Not only that, but I feel more confident to keep going and creating more games that support my vision. I&#39;d like to thank the people commenting on the submission and the whole LD community for making awesomeness all the time. The games I&#39;m seeing are pretty much amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what I learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code your map editor if you have no experience, making a game is already hard enough&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Any) Experience &amp;gt; no experience&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on crucial details early on (but don&#39;t waste too much time on them)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debug tools save minutes to hours of your time&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respect your limitations, make memorable games&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure your house is a nice place to work on games&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s pretty much it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 05:04:17 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/global%20game%20jam/ludum%20dare/2014/05/02/our-first-ludum-dare-game.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/global%20game%20jam/ludum%20dare/2014/05/02/our-first-ludum-dare-game.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Beneath Lights</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;width:70%;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/media/beneath1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Our first Ludum Dare game – Beneath Lights&quot; href=&quot;/global game jam/ludum dare/2014/05/02/our-first-ludum-dare-game.html&quot;&gt;About developing this game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Rafael&#39;s first entry for the Ludum Dare (LD29 theme: Beneath the Surface). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-29/?action=preview&amp;amp;uid=34466&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Check the original entry site here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LD29 happened on 25/04/2014&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
				<link>/games/game%20jam/2014/04/25/beneath-lights.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/games/game%20jam/2014/04/25/beneath-lights.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
